<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief narration of the practices of the churches in New-England. Written in private to one that desired information therein; by an inhabitant there, a friend to truth and peace. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E298_20</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113172</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113172)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 49:E298[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief narration of the practices of the churches in New-England. Written in private to one that desired information therein; by an inhabitant there, a friend to truth and peace. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Weld, Thomas, 1590?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Matth. Simmons for John Rothwell, and are to be sold at his shop, at the signe of the Sunne in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An inhabitant there, a friend to truth and peace = Thomas Weld.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 30".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Congregational churches --  New England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>New England --  Religion --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113172:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF NARRATION OF THE PRACTICES OF THE Churches in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in private to one that deſired information therein; by an Inhabitant there, a Friend to <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Matth. Simmons</hi> for <hi>John Rothwell,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the ſigne of the <hi>Sunne</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113172:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113172:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE NARRATION of the practiſes of the Churches in <hi>NEW-ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>PREFACE.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>r ſcope in this Declaration is onely to anſwer your owne deſire, and cleere our way from ſome miſapprehenſions, which (I plainly ſee) have been ſuggeſted to you againſt our proceedings. what weakneſſe may fall from my pen in this relation, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to my own ſlenderneſſe, not to the cauſe in our hands. <hi>Dirige, &amp; corrige, Jeſu benigniſſime.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur practiſe in Diſcipline conſiſts in theſe ſix heads eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. In gathering or founding our Churches.</item>
                  <item>2. In calling Officers; as, <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Ruling El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Deacons.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. In ſolemne Church-worſhip.</item>
                  <item>4. In admitting of members.</item>
                  <item>5. In recommendations, and diſmiſſions of members to other Churches.</item>
                  <item>6. In cenſuring delinquent members, by
<list>
                        <item>Admonition.</item>
                        <item>Excommunication.</item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>For the firſt; ſuch as do intend to gather into Church-follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note place="margin">1. Gathering the Church.</note> doe often in private meete together, and ſeriouſly examine the ſpirituall conditions one of another, even untill they be mutually ſatisfied, in the judgement of charity of the truth of grace, of each
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113172:3"/>other, of all ſuch as they intend to make the foundationalls of that Church. Which done, they certifie the Magiſtrates, and all neere adjoyning Churches, of their intentions to erect a Church, and the day when they purpoſe to meet in publique for that end; and this is done,</p>
               <p n="1">1. To ſhew they are not aſhamed of the light.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To crave the help of their prayers, and the aſſiſtance of their counſell in ſo weighty a work, being better experienced in thoſe wayes of Chriſt then themſelves as yet are.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To cleere their own proceedings in their Brethrens conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, that they ſeeing their entrance to be according to the Rule, may accept of them more comfortably into communion, as any occaſion ſhall require. When the day appointed is come, and ſome deputed perſons ſent from all the neighbour Churches (which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are the teaching and ruling Elders) there preſent, and moſt part of that day ſolemnly ſpent in faſting and praying for a bleſſing upon that enterpriſe: Then one of them (choſen to order the work of the day) ſtands up and ſpeaks to the other of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that they may now begin to act what they met that day for, which is, to joyn together into holy fellowſhip, if the will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Lord be ſo, and withall, deſires then, that whereas they have manifeſted already Gods gracious workings upon their hearts to each other in private, now they would do the ſame again before the Churches in publike.</p>
               <p>Then himſelf begins,<note place="margin">Confeſſion.</note> and makes confeſſion of his faith in all the principles of Religon, and then a declaration of his effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to Chriſt, and how God hath carryed on the work of grace, <hi>(viz. Repentance from dead works, and faith towards God, both of which they inſiſt upon)</hi> in his ſoule to that day.</p>
               <p>Then all the reſt do the like, which done, to the ſatisfaction of the Brethren preſent, they give teſtimony of the godly and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved life and converſation of each other.</p>
               <p>After this,<note place="margin">Covenant.</note> they enter into a ſacred and ſolemne Covenant, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, profeſſion (call it what you pleaſe) whereby they proteſt and promiſe (by the help of Chriſt) to walk together as becomes a Church of God,<note place="margin">See <hi>Cottons</hi> Way in <hi>New-England,</hi> p. 8.</note> in all duties of holineſſe before the Lord, and in all brotherly love and faithfulneſſe to each other, according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, withall producing their Covenant, agreed on before
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113172:3"/>amongſt themſelves, then read it before the Aſſembly, and then either ſubſcribe their hands to it, or teſtifie by word of mouth their agreement thereto.</p>
               <p>Then the Brethren of other Churches (ſome in the name of the reſt) reaching forth the right hand of fellowſhip unto them, beare witneſſe to their proceedings to be according to God, teſtifie their acceptance of them into brotherly fellowſhip, and do exhort them alſo in the Lord, to proceed according to thoſe beginnings; and ſo prayers made, and praiſes given unto God, and a Pſalme ſung, the bleſſing is pronounced, and the Congregation diſſolved.</p>
               <p>The Churches thus gathered,<note place="margin">2. Calling of Officers. Acts 6.3.</note> they look out from among themſelves ſuch who are fit for office; and if none among them be ſo (though uſually thoſe that joyn into a Church, have one amongſt them upon whom their eye is, for ſuch imployment) they ſeek to the Lord of the Harveſt to direct them elſewhere;<note place="margin">Matth. 9.38.</note> and (becauſe Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts have no ſucceſſors appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Scripture) the ordinary officers we uſe to call,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.10.</note> are
<list>
                     <item>Elders
<list>
                           <item>Teaching
<list>
                                 <item>Paſtors</item>
                                 <item>Teachers.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>Ruling.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Deacons</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The Paſtors office properly, is to bend himſelf to exhortation.<note place="margin">Paſtors. Teachers. Rom. 12.7, 8.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Teachers office to give himſelf to inſtruction in points of doctrine, explication of Scripture, confutation of error, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ruling Elder to order the Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">Ruling-Elders.</note> to look to the life and converſation of the whole Church, and to viſit from houſe to houſe, to ſee how all thrive in godlineſſe, while the other give themſelves to the Word and Doctrine, and all of them together to govern the Houſe of God, and alſo to prepare in private all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters for Church, and to ſurvey the eſtates, and ripen all ſuch as are to be admitted in the Church, before they produce them in publike, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Deacons office is to have a diligent eye, to look into the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the Church, and with a tender heart,<note place="margin">Deacons.</note> and carefull hand ſupply them from the Church Treaſury with ſuch things as they need for neceſſity, conveniency and comfort, and to ſee that none want, but honourably to ſupply them, even before they fall into any extremity, or be forced to crave help from the Church; and therefore he is,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113172:4"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>To Collect diligently</item>
                     <item>To Keep faithfully</item>
                     <item>To Diſtribute carefully</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>the Churches treaſure,<note place="margin">Acts 6.2.</note> that ſo hee may ſerve the Tables, which is the proper work; the Lords Table, Miniſters table, and the poores table.</p>
               <p>To the Deacons office,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deacon.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.3.</note> we would adde Deaconeſſes, where ſuch may be had, according to which ſhould be widowes of the Church, faithfull, approved, and full of good works, who may give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to works of mercy cheerfully; and to be ſerviceable alſo to thoſe that are ſick, when the Deacon ſo conveniently cannot, and ſometime ſo modeſtly may not ſend their help as that ſex may.</p>
               <p>And here behold (by the way) the faithfull and tender care of our bleſſed Lord, that fully provides in thoſe officers for the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of all his Saints:<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> By Paſtors, Teacher, Elders, Deacons, Widowes, and hath given them their names, works, and titles in his Houſe, which are fully ſufficient for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edification of the body of Chriſt, leſſe then which would be too little, more then which would be too much; for if the minde and judgement of his Saints be well infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and inſtructed in what they ought to know, believe and do, (which is the work and office of the Teacher;) and if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience be convinced, the will bowed to holy obedience, the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons rectified and ſet upon their object, (which is the office and work of the Paſtor) if the life and converſation be well ordered al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, (which is the proper imployment of the ruling Elder) and if all things be beautifully ordered and governed in the Houſe of God, in all the adminiſtration hereof, (which is the joynt work of them all together) there and then alſo, if the outward man be provided for convenienly, comfortably, and timely, that no lack be there, no crying and complaining in our ſtreets for want of ſupply (which is the office of the Deacons,) and if the ſick be helped, refreſhed, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, (which is the office of the Deaconeſſe) then there is full pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the neceſſity of the Saints; all which Chriſt hath given us here: theſe we have, and more then theſe, we are like ſix fingers to an hand; now theſe (we ſay) and no others, being the officers which are in our eyes to call, wee proceed to election, and then to ordination in this manner following.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:113172:4"/>
               <p>Firſt, the men that wee are to call to office, are our own mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Election.</hi> Acts 6.</note> or, if members of other Churches, they joyn with the Church which calls them, before they have any propriety in them, or power in the Lord over them, to call them to office in that body; then they are well known and approved by ſome convenient ſpace of triall, ſeeing we muſt lay hands ſuddenly on no man;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.22.</note> and we diſcern, that not only his gifts, graces, and frame of ſpirit are in themſelves deſireable and commendable, but in ſome good mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure alſo ſutable, and fit for that people: For every worthy man is not fit for every godly people, no more then every glove is fit for every hand, nor every key fit to open every lock, though happily it be a key of gold, another of Iron, which is fit, may be better. They being thus approved, the Church her ſelf, over which he is to be an overſeer, calls him, and none other for them: as <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3. thoſe, I ſay, whoſe ſoules hee is to take the charge of, call him, and ſubmit themſelves to his adminiſtration in the Lord, and not ſome of the Church, as the officers only, if there be any, or the people only, but all of us, with joynt conſent, as one man, or at leaſt the greater part, elect an officer over us: So wee reade that the Primitive Church was carried in all their votes and electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,<note place="margin">Acts 1.23.26. &amp; 14.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 23.</p>
               <p>All things thus ripened for election, when wee are to elect a Paſtor, Teacher, or ruling Elder, wee give notice thereof to the Magiſtrate, and all the next adjoyning Churches, who, and when, and to what office we ordain him unto, and intreat their preſence and company with us, for their brotherly counſell and aſſiſtance; when the day is come, and well ſpent in preaching, faſting and prayer, as <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2, 3. then one of themſelves appointed to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the work of the day, ſtands up, and is inquired of the Church, if none after this ſolemn ſeeking of God for his counſell and directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in that weighty work, they ſtill reſolve to proceed in the ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch a one to be Paſtor or Teacher, as before they reſolved to do: Then having taken their ſilence for a teſtimony of their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, hee tells them, now hee ſees all is cleer for his Call, hee deſires the Brethren to teſtifie their votes, in calling ſuch a one to ſuch an office, by holding up their hands: which being done, hee deſires of the party to know if hee accepts of the Call to the office which the Brethren in the name of Chriſt hath given him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113172:5"/>to exerciſe in the Church after his acceptance expreſſed, the Elder requires of the Church to promiſe ſolemnly by Chriſts help to do the duties of a Church to him, as to a Paſtor or Teacher, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſubmit to him in the Lord, to be obedient to his doctrine, to love him, to give that reſpect to him that Chriſt commands and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires: alſo that the ſame ingagement from him, to do all the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Paſtor or Teacher to them.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Election</hi> being finiſhed,<note place="margin">Ordination.</note> they proceed to <hi>Ordination,</hi> which <hi>is nothing but a ſetting apart for, and putting him into that office to which be is elected,</hi> and committing the whole charge into his hands, or laying it on his ſhoulders before the Lord, and this is done by impoſition of hands and prayer. The Elders of the ſame Church (if there be any) do impoſe their hands, if there be none but himſelf is the firſt, then two or three of the principall and moſt grave and eminent Chriſtians, being required by the body, do in the name of Chriſt and the Church; and this is no unuſuall thing in Scripture, as wee conceive:<note place="margin">Numb. 8.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt bring the Levites to be conſecrated before the Lord, and the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> muſt lay their hands on them, and then <hi>Aaron</hi> ſhall offer them to the Lord; ſo alſo <hi>Zadock</hi> the Prieſt was conſecrated,<note place="margin">1 Chro. 29.22</note> and <hi>Solomon</hi> anointed by the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. In time of which impoſition of hands,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> They pray over them for all needfull gifts and graces fit for that great place to which he is called.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They ſpeak the words themſelves of Ordination of him in Chriſts name, and the name of that Church, to that very office.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Put a ſolemn charge upon him, as in the ſight of Almighty God,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.10.</note> before whom hee muſt ſhortly appeare to give an account of all thoſe ſoules committed to his charge by the great Shepheard, Chriſt Jeſus himſelfe,<note place="margin">Num. 27.20.</note> that hee be diligent, faithfull, carefull, and conſtant, in a full diſcharge of that great charge laid upon him.</p>
               <p>After this, the Elders of the Church, ſome in the name of the reſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> do give him the right hand of fellowſhip, in the ſight of all the Aſſembly, and teſtifie their brotherly reſpect unto him: and after thankfulneſſe to God for his gracious gifts beſtowed on him, do exhort him in the Lord, to fulfill his miniſtration received from the Lord; and ſo after praiſes given to God by him, in the name of the Church, hee diſſolves the Aſſembly with a bleſſing.</p>
               <p>For our calling of Deacons,<note place="margin">Deacons.</note> wee judge it not neceſſary (becauſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113172:5"/>we want a rule) to effect it with faſting and prayer, as in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of other Officers, but the Brethren look out from among themſelves men fitly qualified according to the rule of the Word, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.8, 9. and after due approoſe made them, the Elders upon ſome Lords day, or other publique meeting, do or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain him to the office, and appoint him over that buſineſſe by prayer, and impoſition of hands.</p>
               <p>The Church thus gathered and furniſhed with able helpers for edification, proceeds to all publike adminiſtrations in the body,<note place="margin">3. Solemn worſhip.</note> wherein our deſire and care above all things is, to have all, and no more then all the Ordinances of Chriſt himſelf;<note place="margin">Deut. 12.32.</note> and all thoſe (as far as God is pleaſed to lend light) in the native purity and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, without any dreſſings or paintings of humane inventions. Wee uſe not to reade in the publique Aſſemblies,<note place="margin">Reading:</note> Records or Writings of men, but (that alone, which is able to make the man of God perfectly and throughly furniſhed to all good works) the pure Word of God it ſelf; and that all things may be done to beſt edification,<note place="margin">Expoſition.</note> wee uſe to expound and apply the Word unto the people, as occaſion permits; and becauſe we deſire to ſing, (as well as to reade) the pure Word of God, it being an Ordinance of God, as ſacred as the other, wee have endeavoured,<note place="margin">Nehem. 8.8.</note> according to our light and time, to retranſlate the Pſalmes as neer the originall as wee could, into meeter,<note place="margin">Singing of Pſalmes.</note> becauſe the former tranſlation was very defective, and ſing them in the Churches according thereunto. For Prayer, we uſe not any preſcribed formes, or ſtinted Liturgies, but ſeeing the Miniſters of Chriſt are called as well to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to prayer as to the miniſtry of the Word,<note place="margin">Prayer. Acts 6.4.</note> wee pray as that bleſſed inditer of our Prayers (who teacheth what to pray as wee ought) helping our inſirmities, according to the peoples neceſſities, the preſent occaſion, and the work of Chriſt in our hands re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> We adminiſter the ſeals of the Covenant not to all, but only to believers, or their ſeed, which are either in covenant with our ſelves, or with ſome other Church of Chriſt; for though wee verily believe there are many precious Saints amongſt us, who with their children are under the Covenant of Grace, through faith in Chriſt, whom we tenderly embrace, and eſteem deare unto us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſo to Chriſt Jeſus himſelf, and are ready to give to ſuch approved ones, the right hand of fellowſhip, in caſe they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113172:6"/>ſhall deſire it, yet ſeeing ſuch are not liable and ſubject to the Churches cenſure, it is not meet they ſhould partake of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches priviledges, therefore wee have hitherto for born it untill fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light ſhall appeare.</p>
               <p>For the adminiſtration of the Supper,<note place="margin">Sacrament of Supper. 1 Cor. 11.25.</note> becauſe Chriſt bids us do it often, we commonly have it monethly, though wee tie not our ſelves to any ſet time, but alter it as often as good reaſon appeares, and for better remembrance of the duty, and preparation thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, the Elders give notice the Lords day afore, and ſtirs them to an holy preparation for ſo holy a duty: When the time of ſolemn action is come, the Paſtor ſets apart the Elements for ſo ſacred em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he bleſſeth the bread, he breaketh it in the ſight of all the people, declaring withall, and applying the ſignification of thoſe holy Rites and Actions: He diſtributes it to thoſe who be neer about him,<note place="margin">Acts 6.2.</note> and gives the reſt to the Deacons hands, who ſtand ready (according to their office attending on the Table) to give unto all the people, not bowing or kneeling, which are forms of worſhip that never came into Chriſts minde,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.20. Luke 22.27. to 30.</note> ſo far as wee know, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point, nor any way ſutable to a Table-geſture, but in that poſture of body, in which Chriſt himſelf gave it unto his Diſciples: After the bread hee taketh the cup, and bleſſeth it diſtinctly by it ſelf; for ſo our Lord Chriſt did,<note place="margin">Matth. 26.26.27.29.</note> hee powres out the wine, and diſtributes it; this done, a Pſalme is ſung, Prayers returned, and the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation diſſolved.<note place="margin">Mat. 26.30.</note> Wee alſo take our liberty to ſolemnize holy feaſtings and faſting dayes, as God gives occaſion, by his extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary hand of providence of ſpeciall mercy or judgement, either to our ſelves or native countrey, or other churches.</p>
               <p>For the admitting of additionall members to thoſe that are the fundamentalls,<note place="margin">4. Addition of members.</note> we proceed in this manner: Such as deſire to joyn to the church, do make known their deſire to the Elderſhip; who take a ſurvey of their ſpirituall eſtates, both of the knowledge in the principles of Religion,<note place="margin">1 King. 6.7.</note> and of the work of Grace in their hearts; as alſo their blameleſſe and godly converſation among men, in any of which, if they finde any wounded, they plainly declare it to the parties themſelves, labouring by love and patience to heal them and ripen them; where all things are cleer to themſelves, they propound them to the church, and intreat them (as opportunity may ſerve) to take ſome time to deal with them, about their ſpirituall condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113172:6"/>and inquire of the godly approved which know them, that nothing may hinder when they are called to admiſſion: After ſome due ſpace, the ruling-Elders call them before the church in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like,<note place="margin">Confeſſion of faith.</note> who heare them confeſſe their faith in the grounds of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then their effectuall Vocation to Chriſt: Firſt, in their ſound repentance from dead works: Secondly, their unfeigned faith to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37. Then, if they be ſatisfied in both theſe, (as where they diſcern the leaſt true breathing of Chriſt, though but as ſinoaking ſlax, they are) they call (if need be) for teſtification of their godly converſation, which being done, they reſt and teſtifie all their conſents to their admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by holding up their hands; after that, the Paſtor or Elder propounds to them the covenant which they are to make before God and his people, the ſumme of which is to this effect:<note place="margin">Covenant.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To give up one ſelves to the Lord in all duties of holineſſe;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.5.</note> 
                  <hi>then to the Church, and the Officers, in all love and ſubmiſſion, according to the will of God; and this they doe not truſting in their owne ſtrength,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">See <hi>Cottons</hi> way of the Churches in <hi>New-England</hi> pag. 55. more fully expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</note> 
                  <hi>but in the name and by the grace of Chriſt himſelfe.</hi> To this Covenant when they have given their conſent, the <hi>Elders</hi> in their own name, and the Churches reciprocally, <hi>doe covenant alſo with them, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the like duties backe againe unto them:</hi> Then after prayers made by the whole Church, for his gracious aſſiſtance, in performing theſe mutuall duties each to other, and all of them to God, they depart away with a bleſſing.</p>
               <p>If any member thus admitted, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> hath afterward any ſpeciall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to reſide, for any conſiderable ſpace of time,<note place="margin">Of reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and diſmiſſion of members.</note> in ſome other Church; that wee may the better know according to our charge received of them, what becomes of our members, he is wont to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the <hi>Elders</hi> whither he goes, and the occaſions of it; withall to deſire them to propound to the Church for their Letters re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendatory;<note place="margin">Rom. 16.1. 1 Cor. 3.1.</note> which being done, the Church grants it, the ſcope whereof is to teſtifie of the godlineſſe of the man, and to deſire them to receive him as becommeth a Saint, and to be helpfull to him in any thing that may need their aſſiſtance, watchfulneſſe, communion, and edification in the Lord, during the time of his abode with them. The Letter is ſubſcribed by the hands of the <hi>Elders</hi> in the name of the Church, and delivered unto them; but if any member hath a deſire to remove wholly from the Church
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113172:7"/>to which he belongs, and to live elſewhere, he uſeth to make knowne his deſire to the <hi>Elders,</hi> and by their hands to the Church, and where he deſires to live; as alſo the grounds which lead him to ſuch a removall: which if upon examining they prove weake, or ſinfull, ſavouring of ſelfe-will, covetouſneſſe, ſchiſme, or &amp;c. more then of ſound reaſon, and ſuch as are like to caſt him upon eminent dangers, ſpirituall or temporall, then (according to their covenant of love and faithfulneſs) they with tenderneſſe ſhew him his weakneſſe, and diſſwade him from his purpoſe, ſo prejudiciall to his peace and comfort; to which counſell God uſually bows his heart to ſubmit and ſtoope. But if after all the diſſwaſions and brotherly advice, they ſhould ſee the bent of his ſpirit ſtand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a removall, that he cannot comfortably and fully be poyſed by their judgements: In ſuch a caſe, if his ſinne be not apparent, his danger eminent, they uſe ſome indulgence, (not willing to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon the ſpirits of any) and they leave him to his liberty, and permit him to depart; and this we obſerve, that <hi>when men thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, God followes them with the croſſe, till they are driven to repent of ſuch unadviſed proceedings, and deſire to returne to the place which they left.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if they ſee his grounds be good and ſound, and God lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him by the hand, from themſelves to another place, where he may ſit downe comfortably and be edified, they uſe to ſay no more but as they did to <hi>Paul</hi> when Gods minde appeared,<note place="margin">Acts 21.14.</note> to have him leave them and goe to <hi>Jeruſalem (the will of the Lord be done;)</hi> and ſo they write from that Church to the other, Letters of diſmiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſo wee call for diſtinctions ſake, which indeed are all one with Letters of Recommendation, ſpoken of before, onely thoſe were for a time, theſe for ever; wherein they doe uſe to give teſtimoniall of the brother, and intreat them to receive him in all bowells of brotherly love, as their owne in the Lord, and be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his ſoule, untill they ſhall preſent him blameleſſe to the great Shepheard the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; and ſo after godly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell given him to walke worthy of the Lord, in the place where he is to live,<note place="margin">Acts 15.40. &amp; 20.22. This we have added out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </note> they commend him by prayer to the bleſſing of the word of grace. <hi>The Church to whom he is commended, if they know not the perſon, make triall of him, as above, before they admit him, knowing Churches may erre in perſons as well as doctrines, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:113172:7"/>
               <p>So long as the Churches members walke blameleſſe and holy, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> wee encourage them, and comfort them in their godly proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;<note place="margin">Cenſuring delinquents. Gal. 6.1.</note> but in caſe any be fallen by temptation, (as who is exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if corruption preſſe in, and the Lord withdraw?) we pitty him, and labour to regaine him by ſuch meanes as Chriſt hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; as if his ſinne be private, and knowne but to one onely, wee dare not (unleſſe the neceſſitie of the caſe requireth,) communicate it to a ſecond, but uſe to deale in ſecret with himſelfe, and cure him of it: but if this will not ſerve, but either he remaine unconvinced of the evill of it,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> and ſo is like to be hardened through the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of ſinne; then the other takes himſelfe bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if the evill be apparent, to obſerve the rule of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Matth. 18.15, 16.</note> and gradually to proceed further with him, that is, takes one or two more with him, ſuch as are moſt <hi>able,</hi> and <hi>likely to prevaile</hi> with the delinquent brother; and after <hi>prayer</hi> made to God to bow his heart, and boare his eare to attend to their admonition; they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to gaine him to the Lord, from his ſinne; if this meanes prevaile, his ſoule is healed, the offence removed, their love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed: But if yet he remaines impenitent, they enforme the <hi>Elders,</hi> and they tell the Church, the delinquent is convented in publique, and his ſinne laid open, they endeavour to regaine him by opening his ſinne, together with the uneffectualneſſe of the former meanes witneſſed; by which very particular, his former ſinne is much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated upon his conſcience before the Lord, from the Word applyed and preſſed; all which, if even then it ſhall worke kindly, to the melting of his heart into godly ſorrow, and humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, it is acceptable, and no further proceeding attempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But if none of all theſe worketh effectually upon him,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.19. Mat. 18.19.</note> then a ſolemne admonition by the vote of the whole Church, in the name of the Lord Jeſus, by the hand of the <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Ruling Elder,</hi> is ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laid upon him, wherein his ſinne being ſet home with ground from the Word, is left upon him, as ſtronger phyſicke to purge out the diſtemper, which more private and gentle meanes would not effect.</p>
               <p>All the while the Church (imitating the patience of our bleſſed Lord unto our ſelves) is willing to waite, to ſee,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.25.</note> if God at any time, by any meanes, will grant him repentance; which if it ſo be,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113172:8"/>and he come forth and declare it publiquely (for the plaſter muſt be as broad as the ſoare) to the ſatisfaction of the Church, and glory of God, and ſhame of himſelfe, by the humble acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of the evill of his ſinne, and his former impenitency, in withſtanding ſo many precious meanes, ſo patiently uſed towards him, with promiſe by the helpe of Chriſt, for better indeavours for the time to come, the Church proceeds no further, but is ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, comforted, and renders praiſes to the God of all grace, that <hi>hath given us ſuch free uſe of ſuch precious Ordinances,</hi> and hath crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned our poore indeavours with ſuch a bleſſing on the ſoule of his poore ſervant.</p>
               <p>But if he be ſo farre ſhut up under an hard heart, that he departs away impenitent, the Church accounts it, (as indeed it is) a ſore blow from the hand of the Lord, not onely upon the ſoule of the poore brother, but upon them all, who are ſo neerely united unto him,<note place="margin">Joſh. 7.25. to 11, 12. Num. 16.22.</note> and may juſtly make them ſinart, as he did all <hi>Iſrael</hi> for the ſinne of <hi>Achan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As the Church uſeth theſe meanes towards him in publique, ſo the <hi>Elders,</hi> and the godly ableſt brethren alſo, are wont (all this time) to repaire to him in private, if it may be to ſet on the Churches cenſure, and to further the working thereof; and the Church alſo before they proceed to further cenſure, doe call him before them once and againe, uſually, to ſee if the Ordinance in any meaſure be effectuall upon him. All the while that brother (and ſo any other delinquent member, though not ſo fame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt by the Church as he is) ſtands thus offenſive in the Churches eyes, he preſumes not to communicate<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Though he be admitted to hearing and prayer.</hi> Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>way of Churches, pag.</hi> 93. 1 Chron. 28. 1 Cor. 11.28. Hag. 2.13, 14. Levit. 22.3, 4. Agreeably to Mat. 5.23, 24.</note>, or if he does preſume, he is dehorted and prohibited, to eate of the holy bread amongſt the prepared and invited gueſts of Chriſt, as not having by examination prepared himſelfe, as all ſuch are commanded to doe, and for feare he ſhould defile it, as the uncleane under the Law did ſuch holy fleſh as they touched; for looke as the Prieſt that was uncleane, though he was not degraded from his Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, yet ſuſpended during the time of his uncleanneſſe from med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the holy ſacrifice; ſo we deale and that according to God with this uncleane member; and this alſo wee uſe as a further meanes to procure his humiliation, when he ſhall ſee himſelfe through his owne fault barred from the enjoyment of this holy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113172:8"/>priviledge, and muſt now fit and mourne (as the Leper under defilement,) being barred from communicating at the Table of Chriſt, among the holy Saints of God, which he was wont to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy with freedome and comfort.</p>
               <p>But if neither the one nor the other, publique or private meanes are able (no not at laſt) to overcome his hard heart, and bring him to ſound humiliation for his ſinne; then we judge it full time to uſe the laſt and foreſt meanes of cure that Chriſt hath ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Church, even to out off the gangren'd member,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.6, 7. Gal. 5.9.</note> that the whole body be not infected by it; and to purge away the leaven, leſt the whole lumpe be thereby leavened; and for this wee doe not ſend to any externall authoritie out of that particular Church whereof the offender is; whether Biſhop, or Claſſis; becauſe wee conceive it more then <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4. See <hi>Willets Synopſis, edit.</hi> 1634. <hi>p.</hi> 286. 1 Cor. 5.3, 4. 1 Tim. 5.21.</note> (who had more authoritie from Chriſt, then all the Biſhops, Presbyters in the world) dare undertake, who did but <hi>informe, direct,</hi> and <hi>ſtirre up</hi> the Churches to doe it, but <hi>did not doe it himſelfe;</hi> but wee freely uſe the libertie and authoritie which the Lord himſelfe hath given us, and doth charge us to uſe in ſuch caſes as theſe; namely, all the Churches doe ſolemnly meet together, and if it be an open and knowne ſinne, all the Congregation (that they may ſee the Churches im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partiall ſeveritie againſt ſin in her own members) and having ſet the delinquent before us, and having ſet out his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne in the lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and aggravations of it, the <hi>Paſtor</hi> or <hi>Elder</hi> having propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it to the Church, and they having teſtified their conſents (as before for his admiſſion, ſo now) for his expulſion, he ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and of the whole Church, delivers up that man unto Satan,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4.</note> for the deſtruction of the fleſh, and the ſaving of his ſpirit in the day of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>Which dreadfull ſentence being with much feare and trembling, and yet with much power and dread denounced againſt him, hee labours to ſet home the terrors of it upon his conſcience, and doth charge him, though hee hath abuſed all other ordinances, yet to make uſe of this, as being the laſt means which Chriſt will uſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him for his recovery, and withall, warnes him to depart from the Aſſembly and the fellowſhip of the people of God,<note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.14.</note> and withall, directs and charges the Brethren, that they ſo walk to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113172:9"/>him, that hee may be aſhamed and humbled, that what in them lies, they ſhould not hinder, but further the working of that ordinance upon his ſoule.</p>
               <p>And though our proceedings in cenſure be thus ſlow and gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, as we have expreſſed,<note place="margin">See <hi>Cottons</hi> Way of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in <hi>New-England, p.</hi> 92. 1 Cor. 5.11. Matth. 18.15.</note> againſt ſins of a leſſer nature and leſſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, were not ſo much the nature and quality of ſin it ſelf, as the impenitency of the delinquent hath called for the ſharpe cenſure, according to the rule of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16. yet for ſins very ſcandalous and notorious, wee go more quick and roundly to work againſt the offender, and ſtay not to admoniſh once and again, and then pauſe, to ſee how the plaſter works, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we uſe the ſalve, but (unleſſe ſpeedy and very eminent repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which is early ſtept in to prevent, which poſſibly may call to us as a voyce from heaven to <hi>Abraham,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 22.10, 11, 12.</note> to ſtay our hand) wee preſently, without any more ado, meet together, and give up that man to Satan, according to that other rule of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.45.7.11.</p>
               <p>When we have thus caſt him out of the church, wee have not withall caſt him out of our hearts and care, but ſtill attend the cure of his ſoule,<note place="margin">Matth. 9.2. 2 Theſ. 3.6.14</note> by looking to the God of all grace and mercy, on his behalf, doing by him, as they did by the Palſie-man, carry him to Chriſt, when happily hee wants ſtrength to go of himſelf, by following him with private admonition, to help the phyſick the better to work:<note place="margin">Lev. 26.39.40.</note> And if we diſcern his uncircumciſed heart is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and that hee accept of the puniſhment of his iniquity, and confeſſe, that as God hath walked contrary to him, ſo hee hath walked contrary to God, and is ready to judge himſelf before the Lord and his people,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 1.7.8, &amp; 2.6. to 9.</note> taking ſhame to himſelf, and giving glory to God; (in a word) when we ſee Gods end is attained, and the cure of his ſoule effected, then (as before wee called for no externall power from Biſhops, or other Presbyters to bind him, ſo now) wee need no licence nor commiſſion from any to looſe him, but the church her ſelf only,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.6. to 9</note> as ſhee had liberty according to the rule of the Goſpel to take him in, and to caſt him out; ſo now, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve and releaſe him from all the cenſure, who all being met in Chriſts name, and perſwading themſelves, that as Chriſt unlooſed him in heaven,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.7, 8.</note> ſo it is their duty to unlooſe on earth; and ſo their vote being called for by the Paſtor or Elder, and teſtified by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, hee is as the Leper by the Prieſt of old, in the Law, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113172:9"/>clean, and ſo they (as <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to do) they forgive him, they comfort him, they renue their love unto him, and now not only their Temple doores, but their armes and hearts are ready to receive him.</p>
               <p>As the church hath power from Chriſt over a delinquent mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to reject him from their ſocieties, ſo alſo over a ſcandalous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, to deprive him of his office among them (though this wee ſpeak <hi>de jure, non de facto,</hi> for bleſſed be God, we never had any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to put this in practice, and wee deſire wee never may) for as they, and they only had power from Chriſt to call one to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter unto them, ſo they have the ſame power (upon juſt cauſe given, and he making himſelf unworthy and unfit to perform that work they called him to, and to adminiſter holy things with his impure hands) that when they <hi>ſhall ſee one juſt ground that Chriſt himſelf hath diſcarded</hi> from miniſtring unto them, then they alſo may be <hi>Chriſts Inſtruments</hi> to depoſe him from the office they called him unto.</p>
               <p>In all theſe church-adminiſtrations, ſpoken in this Diſcourſe,<note place="margin">Acts 2.46. &amp; 4.25. &amp; 5.12.</note> our great deſire and care is to carry all things with joynt conſent of all the members, which was the practice and honour of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, which <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much deſired,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 2.10.</note> ſhould be in the church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and through Gods great goodneſſe we have obtained that mercy that uſuually in all our admiſſions, diſmiſſions, elections and cenſures, it hath been ſo with us to our great comfort.</p>
               <p>But in caſe there ſhould any difference ariſe (as poſſibly they may through the remaining darkneſſe of our mindes, all not being able to ſee alike) then ſuch as diſſent from their Brethren and propound their grounds which are either weighty from <hi>the Word,</hi> and then it is the voyce not of the Brethren only, but <hi>of Chriſt ſpeaking</hi> in thee, to which the reſt ſubmit and yeeld, or elſe their reaſons have little or no ſtrength in them, which the Brethren are able with eaſe to anſwer; and then either the reſt ſee it and yeeld, or if they are not convinced of the invalidity of their reaſons, and the ſtrength of their Brethrens anſwers, it is either through the <hi>weakneſſe of their judgement,</hi> or the <hi>ſtiffneſſe of their will;</hi> if the former be the cauſe, the reſt lovingly inform them, and patiently beare with them, till things be in ſome ſort cleered up; that they are content wholly to ſubmit and conſent to make no further trouble, which they are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113172:10"/>frequently taught, to do in caſes of ſuch nature, but if ſtiffneſſe of will plainly appeare, or a ſpirit of contradiction, if they will not by loving information lay down themſelves, they think it meet to admoniſh them of pride and wilfulneſs, and leave them under it till they ſhall repent, whereby the liberty of their voyce is taken from them, till they have removed the offence.</p>
               <p>But if the cauſe ſhould be weighty and dark,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cottons</hi> Way of Churches, <hi>pag.</hi> 95. Acts 15.</note> and the doubtigreat on both ſides, wee call in light from other churches, to whom by agreement they repaire, and crave their counſell: This being faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done, by Gods ordinary bleſſing and preſence (to our comfort we ſpeak it) we have found it concluſive and availe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>[That which follows is added out of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Cottons</hi> late booke of the way of the Churches in New-England, that this Narration might be compleat.]</head>
               <p>HItherto of their practice in regard of each Church by it ſelfe, and the members of it: in the next place is to be related what the courſe is in reſpect of many Churches in communion and fellowſhip; and this (omitting that was ſaid before in their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall aſſiſtance about the conſtitution of particular Churches, and recommendation of members, &amp;c.) conſiſts in two points general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (for wee will name onely the chiefe) firſt, the combination in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Synods or Aſſemblies: Secondly, Dealing with Delinquent Congregations.</p>
               <p>For the firſt; When either corrupt opinions, or ſuſpicious practices are ſcattered, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> ſo as they cannot well be healed by any Church alone,<note place="margin">Aſſemblies.</note> the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Churches deſirous to maintaine verity and unity of judgement, in matters of doctrine and integrity of life throughout the Churches, doe both acquaint the <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> being <hi>nurſing Fathers (amongſt us)</hi> to the Church, with the neceſſary occaſions and ends of a generall Aſſembly, and doe alſo <hi>ſollicite the Churches</hi> to ſend ſome fit perſons at ſuch a time &amp; place where the Aſſembly is to be held, to conſider and diſcerne of the matters in queſtion.</p>
               <p>The Aſſembly being met in the <hi>name of Chriſt, and his preſence called for by humble and earneſt prayer,</hi> the matters to be diſcuſſed are
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113172:10"/>propounded by one of the <hi>Elders</hi> of that Church where we meet, or by ſome other appointed by them, and conſented to by the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi> The matters propounded, the <hi>Elders</hi> do declare their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, together with their reaſons from the Word.</p>
               <p>All which time it <hi>is free for any man</hi> preſent, (and <hi>all may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> if they will) as well the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of the Churches, <hi>as others</hi> (<hi>after leave orderly</hi> craved and obtained,<note place="margin">Acts 15.7.</note> to propound their doubts without offence) whence diſputation doth ariſe (as <hi>Act.</hi> 15.7.) till all parties be either ſatisfied or convinced.</p>
               <p>In points which are not ſo fully cleared and agreed upon, or the nature of them ſuch as may admit further diſcuſſion,<note place="margin">☜</note> difference of <hi>apprehenſion</hi> without <hi>diſunion of affection,</hi> or diſturbance of the Churches peace is <hi>permitted,</hi> and each man is left to his <hi>Chriſtian libertie;</hi> ſo farre as <hi>they all attaine,</hi> they judge and minde <hi>one thing; if any be otherwiſe minded, who in ſimplicitie of heart ſeeketh the truth, and in meekneſſe of wiſdome and love, holdeth forth the ſame, wee hope God will in time reveale the ſame unto him;</hi> in the meane time,<note place="margin">Rom. 14.2, 3.</note> all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in this <hi>one, Not to condemne nor to deſpiſe one another in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of weakneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>dealing with,</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> or <hi>admoniſhing of offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Churches.</hi> When a <hi>ſcandall</hi> ariſeth in a <hi>Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Admonition of delinquent Churches.</note> whether by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of <hi>doctrine,</hi> or in <hi>manners;</hi> if upon <hi>diligent ſearch</hi> it prove true, the Church hearing thereof, ſendeth Letters, or Meſſengers, or both, unto the <hi>Elders</hi> of that Church, and exhorteth them to take a ſpeedy courſe to the redreſſe thereof.</p>
               <p>But if the <hi>Elders</hi> prove remiſſe therein, (or be faulty themſelves) they then certifie <hi>the whole Church</hi> thereof,<note place="margin">☜</note> to <hi>call upon their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſent to the Church of <hi>Coloſſe,</hi> to call upon <hi>Archippus, Col.</hi> 4.11.<note place="margin">Col. 4.11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>If the Church heare them not, the Church offended taketh in the helpe of two or three Churches more to joyne with them. If ſtill the offending Church perſiſt in the neglect of their duty, and of the counſell of their brethren, either the matter would be referred to <hi>a Congregation of many, or all the Churches together,</hi> (if need ſhould require) or els if the offence be <hi>evident,</hi> and <hi>weightie,</hi> and of <hi>ill,</hi> though <hi>not of generall conſequence,</hi> the <hi>Churches offended</hi> would (as juſtly they might) <hi>withdraw themſelves from the right hand of fellowſhip,</hi> and ſo <hi>forbeare</hi> all ſuch exerciſes of <hi>mutuall bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113172:11"/>communion</hi> with them; which all the Churches of Chriſt are wont to walke in one towards another; as mutuall 1. <hi>Participation</hi> of Ordinances;<note place="margin">See <hi>Cottons</hi> Way of chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> 2. <hi>Recommendation</hi> of members; 3. <hi>Conſultation</hi> in matters of weight; 4. <hi>Joyning</hi> in Aſſemblies; 5. <hi>Contribution</hi> to their outward wants; 6. <hi>and helping to propagate</hi> ſuch Churches which are (with this 7. <hi>of admonition</hi>) the ſeverall acts of communion which wee hold as Churches one with another.</p>
               <p>And though we have never been put to the utmoſt extent of this duty, becauſe the Lord hath ſo prevented that no church hath ſtood out ſo long; yet if it ſhould ſo fall out (as God forbid) wee look at it as our duty, by <hi>proportion</hi> as one <hi>brother</hi> is bound to be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to another; and by <hi>example of the Church, Song.</hi> 8 8. who lookes for her little ſiſter that had no breaſts; and of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. who took <hi>care of all the Churches,</hi> which <hi>publike ſpirit</hi> of grace and love is not dead with them; all the <hi>Churches</hi> of Chriſt ought to have <hi>a care</hi> and watchfull eye over the <hi>publike good</hi> one of another, though not <hi>virtute officii,</hi> yet <hi>intuitu charitatis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, let all godly minded judge, what errour or iniquity is in our Practice, ſo much cryed out upon by the ſons of men, and ſome of our deare Brethren,<note place="margin">Pſal. 81.5. &amp; 11.3.</note> who cry us down for <hi>Separatiſts, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, Anabaptiſts,</hi> and what not? <hi>The foundations are caſt down, and what hath the righteous done?</hi> Oh, let men ſhew us from the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Word of truth, where our errour lies; let them ſet down a purer pattern before us, and wee hope God will not ſo far leave us, but that he will open our eyes, and bow our hearts to entertain it; but if upon mature thoughts they judge this to be the very Way of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.1. Acts 26.9.29.4. 2 Pet. 5.10. James 1.17. Iſa. 13.12. &amp; 45.4. Lam. 4.2. Pſal. 2.15. Phil. 2.10.15.</note> (as we believe verily God is now about to cleer it, ſo to be to all the world) let them in the name of God, lay away all prejudice againſt our perſons and practices, and follow us ſo far as we follow Chriſt; So wee could wiſh that all men were as we are, ſaving our meanneſs. Now the God of all truth, and the Father of all lights, perſwade the ſpirits of all his precious ones, duly to priſe thoſe wayes of Chriſt, and bow their hearts to ſtoop to the <hi>ſimplicity of the Goſpel</hi> of our bleſſed Lord and <hi>common head, Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> in whoſe bleſſed boſome of love and care, I leave them and you, ever reſting</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Their and your loving</hi> Brother.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
